Susan Vanderplas

Data Scientist

802 17th St., Auburn, NE 68305 (515) 509-6613

srvanderplas@gmail.com

About me I am a data scientist, that is, I transform data into informed decisions by building and interpreting mathematical models. I work with subject matter experts to understand and quantify prior knowledge, then incorporate data to create robust, accurate predictive models. I offer well-rounded statistical skills, programming expertise, and experience communicating statistical information to those outside the field.

Education

Iowa State University

2015* - Ph.D. in Statistics; GPA 3.71 2011 - M.S. Statistics; GPA 3.69

Texas A&M University

2009 - B.S. Psychology and Applied Mathematics; GPA 3.88

Skills

Statistical Techniques

- Estimation
- Prediction
- Risk assessment

Computer Skills

- R (statistical programming)
- SAS statistical software
- Data dashboard design

- Reliability analysis
- Time-series models
- Bayesian methods
- C, C++
- JavaScript
- SQL/MySQL database

- Nonparametric statistics
- Data mining
- Experimental design
- Web server administration
- MS Office

Experience

Statistical Visualization Research 2012-2015

Modeled effectiveness of graphical designs for accurate communication of statistical results.

USDA Soybean Genome Project 2013 - 2015

Identified important features of soybean genetic data, including genes which contribute to disease resistance and increased yield. Created dynamic reports, interactive data dashboards, and other tools to communicate results effectively.

Google Summer of Code Summer 2013-14

Worked to develop the animint package for R, translating R graphics into d3 interactive JavaScript graphics. Participated in the project in 2013, and returned to serve as a mentor for the project in 2014.

R Course Instructor 2013 - 2015

Designed and conducted workshops to teach statistical computing to members of the university and local busi-

ness community.

Statistics Education Applets 2013 - 2014

Created web-based applets to teach statistical techniques interactively. Link: Applets

Industrial Statistics 2012 - present

Served as an informal consultant to a public utility. Accurately predicted the number of plant outages that occurred during the first 24-month cycle using 18-month cycle data.

Iowa Department of Transportation 2012

Examined the effect of road layout and construction on driver safety (collisions, fatalities).

Materials Science Collaboration 2010-2011

Increased accuracy and efficiency of peak detection (vs. manual identification) using robust quantile analysis.